I think one of the things about meta
culture is that it's very engineering
empowered. If you can get engineers to
support something from the ground up,
you can go a long way. And there's a
popular phrase code wins argument, and I
think in this case it's a case of like
proof wins argument.
>> One of the questions that I often ask
when I talk to people about spec-driven
development is at what level are we
talking about? So, what we took was
defining a process using repo 5, how
we're going to work with the LLM
starting with the spec, and then we
paired developers with that process.
There's a Stanford research on over
100,000 employees. What they found out
is AI is helping generate 30 to 4% more
code than before. However, 15 to 25% of
that code ends up being junk that gets
reworked, right? So, they estimated the
actual productivity gain is like 15 to
20%. I would think it's higher if you're
using AI in the right way. All large
tech companies have this issue. Your
software that's been in existence for
more than a few years using legacy that
no longer resemble the way that you
would rebuild those things today. So,
we're talking about shifting to
architecture with a semantic layer and a
query engine on top to serve the same
kinds of metrics queries, but on a
off-production architecture.
[Music]
Before we jump into this episode, I
wanted to let you know that this podcast
is for developers building with AI at
the core. So, whether that's exploring
the latest tools, the workflows, or the
best practices, this podcast's for you.
A really quick ask, 90% of people who
are listening to this haven't yet
subscribed. So, if this content has
helped you build smarter, hit that
subscribe button, and maybe a like. All
right, back to the episode. Hello, and
welcome to another episode of the AI
Native Dev. And we're here live from New
York at QCon AI. And on my journey here,
I'm going to be talking with a number of
different folks throughout the
conference
based on whether I think it's a a really
nailed-on presentation for our
listeners. And today's, I absolutely
found one. And so, this is Supa Karuravi
who gave a session choosing your AI
copilot, maximizing developer
productivity. And that is such a cool
topic, and you actually mentioned a huge
ton of different productivity hacks and
things like that in and around using
various agents and LLMs.
First of all, Supa,
talk to us a little bit about who you
are. You work for Coinbase. What do you
do there? And and tell us a little bit
about it. Yeah, yeah, I'm happy to. So,
I'm
Supa, like the fruit pear, makes it
easier for people to remember. I'm a
machine learning platform engineer at
Coinbase. I've actually only been in the
industry about 2 years. I used to sell
teddy bears. One of a different career.
And I also teach part-time at UC
Berkeley, where I teach people these AI
tools and how to use them to maximize
productivity or launching startups. And
I also run an academy for kids to teach
them the same thing for free, which is
called AI Scouts. It's kind of my
passion project.
>> That's super cool. Super cool. And so,
how what age groups are we talking here?
We actually start anywhere from like 11
and up to 70. Some grandpas want to
learn as well. And we we like put them
all together, but we teach them the
basics of AI, how to like understand
software, and how to use some of these
tools that we're going to talk about
today. Amazing. Amazing. So,
we talked about or rather you talked
about a bunch of different tools, a
bunch of different agents, and you went
through a number of different tips and
tricks to get people to to be more more
proficient, more effective with those
agents and those tools. Tell us a little
bit about what what is your Yeah. What
is your environment that you find you
are and I know this is very personal in
terms of everyone is different, but for
you personally, what's your what's your
ideal environment that makes you the
most productive?
>> Yeah, I think my ideal environment is
Cursor IDE set up with Claude Code on my
terminal, and that's where I feel I'm
the most productive. I'll kind of use
Cursor for most of the things actually,
like 80 to 90% of the things I'm doing
on Cursor. But for deep tasks, I will
start off my task with asking Claude
Code. Oh, wow. Okay. Yeah, yeah. And how
do you find like
Was that the first time you moved out of
IDE into terminal? Yeah, yeah. I How did
you bridge that not being able to see
everything in a kind of like typical
IDE? Yeah, yeah. I think initially why I
started is because our company was
actually tracking developers using AI
and how much they're using it. And
actually in a good way. It's not I know
some companies are like they don't want
to use as much AI cuz it costs a lot,
right? Our company was pushing a lot of
AI adoption. And then Claude Code uses a
lot more tokens than Cursor does. So, it
seemed like I wasn't using a lot of AI
even though I was pretty sure I'm using
AI more than most people. So, I'm like,
okay, let me try out Claude Code because
of the token usage. But it turns out
like it is really useful, right? For
those deeper tasks, I've had so many
projects where Cursor couldn't get it
done, but Claude Code could get it done.
>> Very interesting. Uh and yeah. And why
don't we go through a number of tips
then? So, we'll talk about Cursor first,
then we'll jump into Claude Code. So,
Cursor, you went through I think 14
different tips. They're on they're on
screen. We'll we'll flick through them,
and we'll we'll pull them up as you as
you as you find one that you like. Um
tell us about tell us about a few of the
tips that you find, hey, do you know
what? This is a really a game-changer.
Maybe for Cursor specifically or just
generally. Yeah, yeah. I would assume
most of your audience hopefully is
pretty AI forward. What's it not? For
the people who don't like AI, tab AI is
where I would start.
Cursor has this tab function. For the
people who don't like it, just like turn
on Cursor and see what it suggests cuz a
lot of times it'll like write 10 to 20
lines of code for you from you just
hitting tab and not having to lift a
finger.
>> Yeah. So, that's where I would start for
people who are really against AI.
>> And this is the very agent this is very
AI-assisted kind of like tab completion
levels of of AI use. Correct. Cursor has
their own model built for this AI tab
complete, which is why I recommend it
over a lot of other IDEs. Cool. Okay.
So, tab, what's next? Tab, what's next?
Let's see.
True is like So, I think most people
know about Cursor agent. That's where
you use it, right? But the multi-agent
mode I think is really underrated. And
what I like it for specifically is
there's like a new model coming out
every other day at this point, right?
And like how do you keep up with which
one's the best and which one's not? You
kind of want to experiment. At the same
time, experimenting takes up a lot of
time. So, what I like to do is every
time some new AI model comes out, use
this multi-agent mode where you can set
it up so you type in one prompt and have
two or more AIs answer that same prompt.
Mhm. So, recently with ChatGPT 5.2
coming out, I wanted to see if I wanted
to switch my daily driver from Opus 4.5
to this new one. So, I would have it
almost shadow whatever Opus 4.5 is
doing, see how I like the results, and
then after a few tries kind of decide
like do I want to continue using this or
not. So, multi-agent is a great one for
people to use.
>> That's awesome. That's awesome. And so
and so with this one, how would it once
you parallelize, how do you then choose
which one?
Uh so, there there's like a suite
benchmark for these models where you can
see which one tends to be the best. I
don't think that's the best metric. Like
you can tell like Google Gemini for
example recently ranks really high on
that, but people most of the time are
saying Claude is better. So, comes up to
your personal experience most of the
time. I kind of just take a look at it,
see if it did a good job of completing
it. How do I like the code it generated?
How do I like
the response that it gave. So, for
example, I really like Claude because
the responses it gives a lot of times
are more educational than the other AIs.
You can really understand what it did
better.
So, yeah, I I just leave it up to
personal experience. You look at it,
whatever works for best for you, that's
the one you end up using.
>> Yeah. Another great feature from Cursor
specifically is they built their own
model called Composer. The other IDEs
don't have this model, so it's native to
Cursor.
And it's specifically good at generating
code quickly. The biggest problem we
have a lot of times with these AI coding
is like you type something in and then
you're waiting 2 to 3 minutes. And
sometimes the task isn't even that
complex. For that, I'm using Composer.
So, for example, this page was generated
with Composer in 24 seconds, where
something like relatively similar for
Claude was 2 minutes and 30 seconds. And
the results are pretty similar.
>> And that's significant actually cuz like
I I remember when we like we're
originally like in the very early days
of of um uh
using AI in a more assisted way
particularly and when using the tab
completion for example, we required a
really really fast turnaround, right?
When you hit tab, you want an answer
like within a split second.
>> Yeah. Now, with more agent-based that
that because it goes deeper, you will
be, you know, more inclined to say,
actually I'm I'm I'm happy to wait for
it 30 seconds, a minute, or something
like that for a better answer. But now
actually when you look at this, the
difference between 30 seconds and 2
minutes, 2 and a half minutes, is
significant and actually interrupt your
flow, interrupt your thought process
when it gets that significant in in in
kind of like difference. So, that
actually matters quite a bit. Yeah,
yeah, 100%. It's so big of a problem
that it's like a funny example, but YC
actually invested in this company, which
is a brain rot IDE. It's an IDE that
pops up TikTok videos and games for
people to do while they're waiting.
So, if YC is putting money into it, like
there's a problem there. It's like that
classic meme like my code's compiling,
right? Why are you playing games? Oh, my
my agent's doing something, right?
Exactly. Okay. So,
so yeah, multi-models, what's what's
what else from from the Cursor point of
view, sorry? Yeah. Um
Next big tip is just setting up your
Cursor rules. A lot of people are just
using the agent, but not putting down
like the groundwork you need to do to
really excel with these tools. One of
those is going to be rules. The other
one is going to be MCPs. So, for rules,
there are actually four different types
of rules. You can choose rules that
always apply on every prompt, or you can
have it be specific where Cursor's
figuring out if it should apply it based
on the context, based on specific files,
or you can just have it set up so it
Cursor will never by its own look at the
rule, but only apply it when you
manually tell it, hey, I want you to set
up this rule. Opt-in kind of like
information, opt-in documentation. Very
actually a little bit similar to how
Tesla does that with the Tesla entity
and things like that. Awesome. Cursor
rules really are important. Why is
context so important? Yeah, I think
you kind of got to
treat your AI like a basic junior
engineer. If you don't give them the
full requirements of the task, he's not
going to be able to figure it out,
right? So, we need to make sure all the
details that the AI needs to know, we're
providing it. And I think
one really good way to do that as well
is with MCPs and setting up some sort of
documentation MCP because there's often
time a lot of gaps in our code where the
AI will read through your code, but
still not understand what's going on.
But when we give it access to our
documentation, it can read it that and
fill in those gaps, which will really
really boost the productivity of what
you can produce.
>> Yeah, amazing. And actually in the in
the session I asked one of the questions
which was about how you know, how to
know when to give you know, enough
context without giving so much context
that it actually degrades the
performance. And I guess that's what a
lot of the things like when we talk
about cursor rules and they always apply
and they apply manually, it's for
exactly that reason. And I suspect when
we look at if if you want to if you had
a huge amount of context that you wanted
to provide, you would probably more
likely to say actually there's too much
context here. Let's add this either
manually or add it more intelligently
apply it intelligently so that way
you're not actually bloating context
>> Yeah.
>> for no reason.
>> Yeah. So super interesting and actually
a really really crucial part.
Okay, one more cursor rule and we'll
jump into Claude.
>> Yeah. Yeah, let's do it. You can have a
bunch of different rules. I think one
that's particularly interesting Claude
shared this themselves is relating to
this context we just talked about. Often
times if you get close to the end of
your context window so you've used up
like 90% then you ask the AI for
something, it will give you a short
answer because it's just trying to get
something out before it runs out of
context. But if you type in a prompt
like this or something similar, you can
tell it, "Hey,
your your context is going to end but
like don't worry about that. You can
compact it. Actually give me the best
answer." And that's one useful tip.
Yeah. One things I love and actually
maybe this segues us into Claude. One of
the things I love particularly about the
slash the slash command the compact
is the fact that you can add some text
after that which is super cool cuz if
you do a slash sometimes it'll auto
compact or you just put slash compact
which will which will make it compact. I
love the slash compact where you put
text after it and that text is, "Hey,
this is what I'm going to do next." And
what that'll do is
it'll also it'll based on that it'll
release a a certain amount of context
that it doesn't need because it thinks,
"Actually I I don't need that for my
next task."
>> Ah. Super super cool way of actually
saying actually I want you to release
just the right context and leave me with
what I need to do my next task. So
that's a a Claude tip.
>> That's a good tip. That's a good tip. I
like that tip. And that leads us into
Claude Code. Now Claude Code I would
probably say is probably one of the most
functional agents in terms of the extra
value add that it provides you with.
Let's jump into the Claude Code section.
What I what would you say
is your kind of like number one tip for
for Claude Code?
>> Yeah, I guess
Claude Code very similar to the way I
use it that I do on Cursor except I
think the use cases are different.
Cursor's good cuz it gives you
the visual ID. You can see what you're
doing. It's faster than Claude Code is,
uses less tokens, and you can switch
between different AI models. But if
you're trying to go deep on a task
that's difficult, Claude Code does a lot
more thinking, takes up a lot more
tokens, but usually gives you a better
engineered answer.
>> Yeah. And like at work I had a project
like this that I put into Cursor and
into Claude and Claude Code saved me a
ton of time. It like searched the web,
found open source repos, analyzed them,
gave me a proper solution where Cursor
just like picked something, implemented
it, and it was done, right? But Claude
Code really saved me like multiple
hours. And I think based on your
language that you use in the prompt, it
will do the correct amount of thinking
based on that. So if if you type think
deeply, it actually adds the amount. And
if you another top tip, if you type in
ultra think, I don't know if you've
typed that. Let's go let's go to the
terminal quick.
If you type in if I was to go let's run
Claude. If you type in ultra think I'll
ultra
think it does this crazy thing.
>> I didn't even know about this. This is
one of like the lowest the deepest
levels of deep thinking it will do. And
so if you if you type something after
that, it'll then go in and do really
deep thought on that on that thing.
That's a good one. So super cool super
cool little tip there as well. So
thinking yeah I I totally agree. And I
think that's why sometimes Claude takes
that deeper like longer time because it
does do that deeper thinking. So
thinking completely agree with that.
Next tip, what's up?
>> 100%. Other than sub agents, this is
where Claude Code kind of beats out
Cursor as well where you can set up
different agents and give them all their
specific MCP tools that they can use.
And these sub agents also have their own
context windows. Yeah. So for more
complicated tasks, this might be a a lot
better. For example like you might set
up a sub agent that's a PagerDuty
investigation sub agent, right? Every
time a page comes in
and you call Claude Code, it'll use this
one. It'll specifically look at Slack,
find the alert, and then go into
DataDog, research it, and come back with
a solution for you. But for specific
workflows that need specific sets of
tools, these sub agents can be super
helpful.
>> And all that extra all that extra work
it did adding stuff into the context
unnecessarily just to get a small amount
of information, it passes that small
amount of information information back
to the main agent and then all that
other context just gets lost, right?
>> Exactly. Exactly. So useful. We use that
at Tesla a lot to do our research on our
on our kind of like our context. And
then we once we learn this is the piece
of context we need to pass back to main
main agent, it's it keeps it nice.
>> Yeah. Yeah, 100%. Context management is
like kind of everything. Absolutely. Now
sub agents, that's not a that's not a
thing which is which is duplicated
across many different agents, right?
It's it's quite particular to Claude in
terms of I would say the mainstream
agents. Do you feel like you know,
agents are going to learn from each
other and start building these
additional things? Do you feel like
we'll hit a
a kind of like feature parity across
these agents or how do you see that? I I
think it really depends to how companies
handle this context management problem.
But right now even with Claude Code,
there's a main agent and sub agents and
none of the sub agents actually talk to
each other. The sub agents all talk to
the main agent. So even Claude Code
itself isn't like that advanced of what
we could be doing in the future and I'm
sure these companies will start to
dabble in that.
>> Really interesting. There's also another
tool I think it's called Claude Flow
which whereby they do kick off a whole
ton of agents. I think it's yeah mostly
command line. And they have this thing
called Hivemind which is super cool
where the agents have almost like this
shared memory where they can start
writing to that memory and learning from
each other. So yeah, audience if you're
interested in that, I think it's Claude
Flow which is which is super cool.
Sub agents super cool. Really love that
about Claude.
Another tip while you're introducing
other tools, Claudish is another one.
Really love like the terminal of Claude
Code but you want to use different AIs
with it. There's different open source
libraries that do this but Claudish is
one of them. Looks exactly like Claude
Claude Code but you can call like
Gemini, ChatGPT, whatever AI model you
want from it. And that's and people
would do that because they love the
Claude Code UI your DX UX but they
presumably have a different model that
either the company have agreed on or
something like that. Do you think you'll
get like a much of a benefit in terms of
the
the underlying LLM being maybe certainly
better in certain cases or not or do
would you say
you know, if you don't care, Claude Code
is probably better to use Claude with. I
I I think if you don't care, Claude Code
is probably the best to use at this
point. Maybe that changes.
I wouldn't really recommend Claudish.
It's just exactly for that specific use
case I just explained.
>> are tied, it's a good Another thing is
like when you're using these AI tools,
it's important to evaluate like are
these actually working or is it slowing
my team down? A lot of times actually
initially teams will adopt AI and see a
little bit of slow down before they ramp
up and that's kind of the learning curve
that it takes to start using these
tools. But overall you want to be
tracking these metrics.
There is no perfect metric is what I
found, right? But what you want to do is
just track a bunch of different things
like PRs merged, how long from a PR
created to merge, etc. And then like
what I find most times is you and the
company build a qualitative story that
you want to tell your management. But
when you have these metrics, you can
pick and choose which ones you need to
use at the right time to tell that story
and back it up with evidence. So that's
where I think it's like really important
to gather as many different metrics as
you can and use them when you think it's
right.
>> agree more. I think I think
in the past AI adoption has more been
like people were just wanting to adopt
AI tooling and they they have that
almost that push from up top like you
have to be using AI. Let's let's all do
it. And I think there are certain people
who are now looking at this thinking
from a productivity point of view, how
much value is this providing me? I was
talking with Tracy Vannin yesterday
actually and Tracy who's giving the
closing keynote actually at the QCon.
And hopefully we'll chat to her as well
but Tracy was talking about value versus
things like velocity cuz velocity is
just a metric, all right? It's a metric
and it can be it can be gained. Like
there's a whole different ways. But
value is super important. It's like what
is this what is what is this agent
actually giving to us from a business
value point of view? I think it's super
crucial. Completely agree with you. I
think I think the practice 100%.
Kind of alluding to what you're talking
to,
they have some complicated research
methodology that they did over on a on
over 100,000 employees but the what they
found out is AI is helping generate 30
to 4% more code than before. However, 15
to 25% of that code ends up being junk
that gets reworked, right? So they
estimated the actual productivity gains
is like 15 to 20%. I would think it's
higher if you're using AI in the right
way. But good to know. Like there's a
difference between value and just
straight output. Absolutely. Yeah, and
that's the that's the biggest trip has
it to just to just you know, output
versus outcome and measuring that
measuring that wrong thing. 15 to 20% is
still still impressive and we expect
that to probably grow as well every time
when LLMs etc. 100%. Amazing session
today. Thank you so much. I appreciate
it appreciate it to be in it and and
meeting you at QCon today.
>> Thank you for having me. Absolutely.
Enjoy the rest of the conference and and
yeah, speak to you soon.
Hello and this time I'm with Ian Thomas
who is a software engineer at Meta. So
Ian, welcome to our podcast.
>> for having me. And and your as soon as I
saw your title
on the on the schedule, I thought I have
to have Ian on my on the podcast because
your title today was AI Native
Engineering. And of course this is the
AI Native Dev podcast and I'm like
that's a perfect match. That's a match
made in heaven. So tell us a little bit
about the session. So this is kind of a
case study of what we've been doing in
my team and my wider org in the Reality
Labs part of Facebook and Meta
where we've had a sort of ground-up
adoption program for people who are
looking to experiment and and develop
with AI
as part of their workflows. Building on
all the various tools that we've been
getting access to over the last few
months
and generally seeing how we can
accelerate ourselves in in terms of
productivity and making more
I guess wins product wins and outcomes
for our teams. And and I guess in terms
of like every organization is different
but generally how would you say how
would you say adoption is of these types
of tools in a in a large organization
like Meta. Do you have like people who
are diving in, people who are stepping
back, and then the majority maybe
leaning into it slightly? Or where where
where where does that sit?
>> So, I I'd say
well, it's changed a lot over the last 6
months. So, um I can only really speak
to my org and the patterns that I've
seen there. We had a few people that
were really keen and and sort of
experimenting, and they were they were
finding value of these tools outside of
work.
>> Mhm. And they were really keen to see
how they could apply it to internal Mhm.
uh Meta has some interesting engineering
things because it's very in-house. It's
it builds its own tools and platforms
and things. So, it's there's
some quite bespoke ways of working there
that maybe you can't just go and pull
some of these things off the shelf and
and apply them to our code base.
>> Yeah. Um but yeah, so we had these few
people that were really passionate about
it, and then we had a bunch of really
senior engineers who were perhaps a
little bit more skeptical. And then
gradually over time, we've seen adoption
grow, and there's been more of a push
from um the the company overall in
saying, "Look, this is going to be
something that we have to take
seriously." Yeah. Um you've got access
to all these tools. Let's go for it. So,
the adoption now is pretty good. I think
last time I checked, we were over 80%
weekly active users.
>> Oh, wow. Uh and the way that we measure
that sort of changed subtly. So, now
it's um
considering four days out of seven usage
of any AI-assisted tool. And can you say
what tools you're using or Uh well,
we've got a whole spectrum of internal
things. So, we've got Meta Mate and Dev
Mate, which are the kind of two main
ones. One's more of a chat interface,
and the other one's more for like coding
and agency workflows.
Um there's a whole bunch of stuff like
Gemini, Code uh sorry,
Gemini,
Codex,
uh Claude Code, um
etc. We've got yeah, access to
third-party tools as well. So, there's
>> a there's a kind of like trying to find
what works for them, and teams are
trying to work out what works for them.
>> Exactly. Exactly, yeah. And a lot of the
tools like um Meta Mate and Dev Mate
have access to the models used by things
like Claude Code as well. So, you get to
compare like things that have got a bit
more internal knowledge than external.
So, it's it's quite good. Yeah. The
versions that we use generally are kind
of tailored for
um Meta use cases. So, they're kind of a
bit more restricted than the generally
available stuff, but they're still
pretty pretty powerful. One part of your
your session that really resonated with
me was when you started talking about
community and growing that community.
Why is why is building that community so
important when we talk about sharing
that knowledge and kind of that growth
and adoption? Mhm. So, I think one of
the things about Meta culture is that
it's very engineering empowered. Mhm.
And so, what that means is if you can
get engineers to support something from
the ground up, you can go a long way.
And uh there's a popular phrase, "Code
wins argument." And I think in in this
case, it's case of like proof wins
argument. So, if you've got people that
are going to be forming around this idea
and these concepts, they can bring them
up to a level where people are saying,
"Hey, I'm getting value from this, and
this is how I'm using it, and this is
what's working." It attracts other
people who go, "Okay, well, if that
if they're doing it, then you know,
maybe this will work in my case, too."
And I think that community aspect helps
to get a bit of authenticity and and
people feeling like they're part of a
community, and it helps to kind of push
everything along with a bit more
momentum. Whereas sometimes, if you get
like a top-down mandate,
engineers we can be quite skeptical
people at times, you know, it's a bit
cynical. And uh so, it's not a well, if
I have to do it, so. But rather, it's
it's bottoms-up. It's a bit more kind of
okay, we can make this work, and I think
it's going to be a great thing. So, what
was being shared then? Like
problems of when peop- people were
having problems or people had questions,
uh wins maybe? Were people saying, "Hey,
this works really well for me." Maybe
context or or rules, things like that?
How did the community work?
>> All of the above, right? So, we have One
of the things that we rely on a lot is
Workplace, which is sort of like the
professional layer on top of Facebook.
Uh it wasn't an external product until
fairly recently. So, we use this
heavily. And that's kind of the basis of
where this community is, and we share
things in there. You can post, people
can comment. It's very it's like a
social experience, but for work. Um
and so, what we were seeing was people
coming in, they were asking questions.
They were saying, "Well, I'm trying this
thing." Or, "Have you seen these tools
available?"
Um generally kind of keeping everyone
informed about what's going on.
And over time, it's just gradually grown
and grown. Um we never really forced
anyone to join. It's not like it's got
like auto-enrollment or anything. And uh
I think last week, we hit 400 members.
Yeah. Which is pretty good for something
that's kind of a grassroots initiative.
>> Yeah, self-sustaining like well, some of
the best communities are like that. And
I guess one of the things that are
really nice about communities is that
everyone, you know, you get so many
different people at different levels of
their experience and adoption. And and
this kind of like leads into one thing
that you mentioned as well, which is
like these maturity models. Like I guess
there's maturity in terms of how an
individual is using it as well as a
team. Talk us through the maturity
models and why they're important. So,
the the thing about the maturity model,
I intended it to be used for a team, but
there is a a dimension on there which is
about individual productivity as well.
So, you can reflect on your own kind of
performance and ways that you're getting
value from it. Um the benefit of it
being a team-based thing is that it
opens up the conversation within your
team. Yes. And so, you can generate uh
ideas and have action plans that are
specific you because every team's going
to have slightly different context or
different levels of ability and
different interests. So, that's great.
Um we tried to model it in a way that
was going to be fairly agnostic of the
tooling and and be durable because
again, the value I think is that you can
have these models, and you can repeat
the the assessments time after time and
see how you're progressing. Um and we do
subtly tweak it every now and again, but
um generally, it's kept fairly
consistent. Uh and then yeah, like I
said, the teams run these assessment
workshops, and they can have the
discussion. And that's that's where the
real value lies. Yeah, yeah. Let's talk
about value and wins. What were the what
were the big wins that you saw, and and
how did you share that across the
community? So, initially, the wins were
people saying, "Oh, I've been using Dev
Mate, which is part of our our tool set
in VS Code that we work with on a
day-to-day basis. I'm finding ways to
use this to like understand the code
base better or or what have you." And
there were some early examples of people
just sort of
going for a a big problem and and
putting a prompt in, and they were
getting a bit of lucky. And then there
was equally some people that were
suffering that wasn't working at all.
>> Yeah, yeah. Um but then we found there
was kind of repeatable patterns emerging
around things like
um testing improvements or how to make
code quality improvements or reducing
complexity of code. Yeah. Uh and that
was when we started to experiment with
things like unsupervised agents. And you
could say, "Okay, with this category of
problem, um say like we've got test
coverage gaps. We want to go and find
all the files that are related to this
part of the code base related to this
on-call, say. Uh
find the ones that have got the biggest
coverage gaps, and then using this
runbook that we've put together, go and
go and cover them. Go and go and produce
diffs that help us to
bridge the gap."
And that was the sort of thing that we
take
um lots of hours of manual work and
>> Yeah.
as this sort of evolved, we found
actually we can go and use the tools to
go and query the data, find make do the
analysis, and then generate the tasks
for itself to go and then fix the tests
and add the coverage. Uh and I think the
end result was something like 93 and a
half percent coverage was achieved,
which when we were way less than 60% to
start with.
>> Yeah, yeah. Um many diffs landed. And it
sounds like like, you know, huge
productivity gains. Yeah, so that one I
think we ended up doing it in about 3
hours to to achieve this, so, which is
incredible. And this is again, it's one
engineer was just saying, "I've got a
hunch. I think this is going to work.
I'm going to go and play with it."
They found a pattern that works, and
then it became repeatable. They shared
it to the group. And I think I said in
the talk, um one of the things that came
about from that was another engineer was
like, "Hey, this kind of works. I've got
all these tests that are running, fine,
but they're a bit slower than I need
them to be to be eligible to run on
diffs.
I wonder if I can do the same sort of
thing. Can I go and put this tool to use
and and go and find all the tests and
see if I can Mhm. reduce the run time
down."
And I think they they achieved something
ridiculous like 1,900 tests were
improved. Wow.
>> And so, that's
it's a huge amount of work that you
could have done, yeah.
>> time that is, and it's probably you're
probably right, it just wouldn't get
done. So, it's a beneficial increase in
quality versus just time saved. Exactly,
yeah. And then in terms of the value of
that one, I think the real I was
chatting with that in- individual
engineer as well, and I said, "Look,
what would be amazing to know is not
just how many tests you fixed or
improved, can you tell me how many
issues that's actually caught because
they're now eligible to run on these
diffs?" And he went away, and he found
the data. He's like, "Yeah, look, I've
in the time since I launched this, at
least 200 changes have been stopped
because these tests now run, and
previously, they didn't. So,
>> that's the kind of it's harder to get
those kind of value metrics for
everything, but that's the sort of thing
that I think will it makes the
difference, and it helps to persuade
people that this is this is going to be
a different
>> Yeah, yeah. And we're just starting.
Yeah. Amazing. Well, thank you so so
much for for the session and joining our
joining our discussion here. Um I very
very much encourage folks go to the QCon
website, uh check out the talk in full.
Uh but for now, Ian, thank you very very
much. Appreciate it. No problem. Thanks
for having me. Hi there. Now, I am with
uh David Stein, who is a principal AI
engineer at ServiceTitan. And uh and
David gave a a really great session uh
yesterday, in fact, which was called
Moving Mountains: Migrating Legacy Code
in Weeks Instead of Years. Uh very nice
title.
Really really engages the thought
processes of of what is possible with
migrations in and around AI. Um David,
first of all, tell us a little bit about
what you do. Tell us a bit about
ServiceTitan.
Right. So, ServiceTitan, we're the
operating system of the trades. And so,
what that means is this is for uh
service trades and uh
residential, commercial building
services industries like plumbing,
electrician, HVAC, roofing, garage door,
and so on. Much of these contractor
businesses for uh for regular service
work and for construction, ServiceTitan
builds a technology platform that helps
these businesses run their business. So,
end-to-end platform supports
everything from uh you know, customer
relationship management taking payments
to answering the phones. And we have a
whole suite of capabilities in our in
our platform around those around
everything you need to run a business
like that. Uh so, that's what
ServiceTitan is. And I work as an AI
engineer, principal AI engineer at
ServiceTitan.
And
uh
you might wonder like at first, what is
what are the AI use cases in the trades
businesses? And there's actually like a
lot of really interesting AI
applications that are really important
for companies that want to run
a sophisticated operation uh
today. And just to name a few of them,
if that's Sure. I can keep going there.
So, there's
um
one thing that we are doing is around um
what's called job value prediction. We
can
a lot of
trades businesses, when they have
uh you know, many dozens of technicians
and lots and lots of customers and you
know, many jobs that they're going to
serve in a particular day, they have a
uh a big task to do at their at their
main office around matching which
technicians are going to serve which
customers on a particular day. And we
have a bunch of intelligence in our
product that allows for this scheduling
and dispatch to be matched efficiently
to basically help our customers run
their business better, more efficiently.
And uh
that's one example, but there's a bunch
of other areas too. using like for
example, we have uh a voice agent
product uh
that, you know, voice voice AI answering
service so that our customers can kind
of
answers the phones for our customers so
that it can help their customers
schedule service appointments 24/7. Uh
those are a few things that that I work
on.
Um yeah.
>> Yeah. And so, tell us And so, what what
are the big things uh
about your session was about how you
took some legacy application
and you wanted to migrate it. So, first
of all, why don't we talk a little bit
about the the legacy application? Uh you
know, what what were the you know,
pieces of that application
that you needed to migrate? There was a
bit of data, I think. There was some
code. Anything else? Yeah. So, in the
talk, it actually focused on
a a a different area than the things
that I just mentioned.
And it related to a migration that we've
been working on as part of like This is,
you know, like all large tech companies
have this issue if you've been around
for more than a few years. You've Yeah.
You know, your your software that's been
in existence for more than a few years
using
uh you know, legacy
uh you know,
using your components that have been
around for for some time, not you know,
that no longer resemble the way that you
would rebuild those things today using
more state-of-the-art foundations. And
so, anyone who's been in software
engineering, you know, hit for long
enough has had to work on a migration at
some point where you are you have to
kind of unpack code that was written a
long time ago. Uh maybe the people who
wrote it aren't on the team anymore. You
know, where not all of the context is
easy to find, but you have to do the
work of picking those things up and
moving them into a new implementation on
an improved platform. And those kinds of
projects, you know, that all companies
have these projects, ServiceTitan
included, they're notorious for being uh
you know, they take a long time. There's
a lot of kind of toil in understanding
the old legacy code and moving it over.
So, the example I talked about in the
talk was around our reporting
application. ServiceTitan has a
uh a reporting product that basically
allows our customers to see all sorts of
business metrics and KPIs relating to
their operations and their financials
and and their business. And we have a
bunch of
very complex infrastructure that
supports that. And something that we,
you know, do periodically is move the
the underlying machinery to use better
and more state-of-the-art uh
infrastructure. And so, that's what this
is about. So, the specifics are we've
been working on uh you know, like
working with uh DBT MetricFlow. It's
like a metric store technology based on
and layered on top of Snowflake. Those
are some of the details of of the stack
underneath.
Um but there's this big task of how do
you take
uh
this code that was written a long time
ago
touching
uh you know, legacy uh
Well, I I don't know how many of these
dirty details I should go into here, but
like you I'll let you actually ask the
questions. What do you want to know?
>> bit. So, what do we talk about the AI
piece first of all? So, so we know
there's a report that says it's a
reporting part of the application. There
was some code that I think you said you
changed language on for that. There's an
amount of data as well, of course. Did
the data migrate or is that was that
pretty much staying where it was? Um
so,
yeah, so we're we're talking about
shifting from an architecture that is
based on a you know, the legacy stack,
which is written in C# with a ORM, you
know, programming model that is uh
operating against
uh you know, SQL DBs in production and
shifting that to a kind of uh data lake
like architecture with a semantic layer
and a kind of a query engine on top of
that allows us to serve the same kinds
of metrics queries, but on a
off-production architecture. And there's
lots of reasons for that, but the uh is
that what you're
>> Yeah, yeah. No,
that's the one. And so, in terms of So,
you used agents to to help you with
this. Right. Um from the What what would
happen if you just said to an agent, you
know, here's my environment. I need you
to migrate this.
Create a plan. Do it yourself. Right.
What what what would be the problems?
So, for a product like this, when you
have hundreds of metrics and each of
them are underpinned with a bunch of
code written in C#, you know, with all
with all the issues I mentioned before
about not all the context necessarily
being exactly where you need it, there's
a lot of complexity in that. You can't
just open up even the state-of-the-art
coding tools like Cursor and say, "Hey,
please like migrate all of our metrics
into you know, into this new abstraction
on this new framework. And by the way,
convert from C# into writing SQL with
YAML for MetricFlow on top." You it
doesn't uh it doesn't work to do that
and is what we found. Um in order to get
traction there, you have to really break
down
Mhm. the
break down the mountain of that problem
into small pieces. It sounds kind of
obvious if you say it in this way. You
break it down into standardized into
into You break it down into basically a
bunch of similar tasks that can be uh
verified in a standardized way. Yes. And
then you assign a long you you basically
construct a long task list with with
with phases for individual sections of
the task like move these first five
metrics as, you know, the first phase
and then the next and so
>> And who's doing this? Is this is this
humans doing this? Is this humans with
agents as an assistant?
>> Right. So, humans are you know, choosing
the the task list. Right. Like our
enumerating, okay, these are all of the
metrics that we're going to enumerate
and that we're going to migrate in phase
one and these are the metrics that we're
going to migrate in phase two. So,
humans are making those choices as well
as like what the target architecture is
that we're going to be putting these
things into. And humans are also, you
know, with some help from like AI tools,
are constructing the you know, all of
the context that's going to go to the
coding agents to actually enable them to
do the migration work for those pieces.
Mhm.
And you went up into a bunch more detail
in the talk. I very much recommend it's
recorded talk, I believe. So, it's very
very much recommend folks go to the QCon
site and check that out. Um but in terms
of the agents, like now we have those
tasks. The agents now need to take those
bite-size tasks. They need to perform
that migration. And then essentially,
you can run the validation to say, you
know, did this work? Did this not work?
What needs to be changed after that? In
terms of I'm really interested in what
needed to be done to the agent to best
prepare it for that for that actual
migration.
>> Yeah. It's kind of hard to say it all
without the visuals of
talk. So, we can
watch the talk if they want to see more
of these details. But we talked about
standardizing the tools
that need to be used to do each of these
tasks.
And so, that means standardized tools
for context acquisition. So, the agent,
just like an engineer, is going to need
certain context in order to be able to
migrate one of these pieces of metrics
code. What type What type of context
here are we talking about? Context in
the like in terms of the um
what the underlying data looks like in
the database. So,
the the agent will be looking at the
reference code and it will have
references to some tables. And we you
need to know like what some example data
actually looks like that lives in those
tables and what the schemas of those
tables are.
And that's a And And in terms of what's
available in the destination platform.
Like confirming like, okay, we have this
table in Snowflake. We know that the
data is there.
Understanding even uh you know,
anything that a human engineer would
need to see in term in order to be able
to correctly write the code that's going
to calculate these metrics in the new
platform. We want the agent to be
equipped to see that, too. So, we would
have a standardized tool for context
acquisition. Uh or a set of tools. And
we would Like we would What that would
mean is like uh not tools in the sense
of actually MCP. We didn't get that
complicated with it. We just made sure
that the CLI tools, which is
CLI tools that a engineer would be able
to use to get these things, that those
are like set up and ready for the agent
to use to be able to get access to what
it needed in order to be able to do the
task. Then the other really important
piece is around
um
giving the agent a kind of environment
in which to run the code and a kind of
simulation engine like a like a physics
engine in the talk, which is not really
about physics, but it's about a script
or a program that the agent can run
to try out the code that it has written
to actually run the metrics code in a
context that resembles a legacy
application so that it can produce an
output that can be directly compared to
the output that would be produced by the
the legacy code. And I think what you
said in the session was that you're not
using production data at this point.
It's almost dummy data for a little bit
to say if you mess up, I don't I want
you to mess up in a safe environment,
but it it gives a good enough way of you
being able to say and validate almost.
Yes.
>> Yeah, I see what you're doing. You're
within an environment where you can
almost like test yourself and make sure
you're able to migrate and we can
understand Yes.
>> And so from a validation point of view
then or a validator's point of view,
trust is a massive piece of this, right?
In terms of when you when you push big
pieces of code and things like that, um
what levels of validation did you have
there? You obviously mentioned, you
know, you had this like environment that
you created. What else did you need to
do before you kind of like said, "Right,
we're going to put this live." Right. So
it
the validation that enables the tasks to
be able to be done automatically by the
agent,
we had we have
machinery there that can compare the
output produced by the new system to the
output produced by the old system.
And so
um
there's a separate set of validations
that we also run before actually doing
production cutover because it's
obviously extremely important that the
data be right when we're showing it to
our customers. In terms of the details
of those,
I'm not sure what level of specifics go
into there, but hopefully I don't
>> what's what's important is you were you
were effectively replaying things that
you sin saw in your previous production
environment and you were ensuring that
the output that you got from from your
previous production environment was, you
know, the same and equivalent of what
you were getting with the with the
updated code, the updated flows. Yeah,
that's right. So replay is a good
keyword there. So we of course have like
the
logs of what queries are given to the
old system. We're able to play those
queries against this engine that runs
using the new platform as well. Um yeah.
In in terms of the LLM itself um
and the agent itself,
how smart does that actually need to be?
Is it does it like, you know, did you
hit any limitations in terms of oh, we
need to change model or anything like
that or was it pretty basic in terms of
what it actually needed to do given the
context of validated intelligence?
>> I had
a couple slides about this.
At one level, the agent doesn't need to
be that smart. It doesn't really need to
be as smart as a human engineer. Part of
the point that we tried to I tried to
make in the talk is that as long as you
have that kind of self-healing loop
where you're able to empower the agent
to check its work
um and then
try to make corrections if it
didn't you know, if
didn't pass validation and the
uh
the metric computed by the new system
doesn't match the metric
uh produced by the old system. Uh it's
kind of interesting. This project really
kicked off for us when uh Claude 4
Opus was released in I think it was May
of this year.
We had done some experiments before that
at seeing how well the different coding
LLMs could understand some of our legacy
metrics code and it turned out that like
they could
understand it to an extent, but the um
the first time that we encountered, you
know, the ability the LLM to really be
able to understand that stuff well
enough to do a pretty good job of of you
know, rewriting the restructuring the
code for the new platform was with uh
Claude 4 Opus, which is one of the
bigger, you know, models that's out
there. So it So it needed in our case to
be pretty smart, but it doesn't need to
be perfect, which is important point cuz
I think that sometimes people kind of
get caught up in like, well, you know,
bots will hallucinate sometimes and you
know, are they really as good as a human
engineer, but like part of what I'm
trying to say is that that's not the
point. As long as you can have the
self-healing loop. So So it's
interesting that you needed that kind of
like Opus 4. Did Did Did they Did they
get stuck at any point? Were there any
common kind of like ways in which the
agent or the LLM failed maybe through
lack of context or or or, you know, lack
of
uh
intelligence or anything like that?
>> Yeah, so we have a slide about this as
well.
So the um
in in the in the talk we talked about a
few pieces that we put up to kind of
govern this process where you're going
to have the agent go through and do
these tasks one after the other. And the
it's not the case that we came up with
this idea and we tried it one time and
it was able to just do all of the
metrics and migrate all of them in just
one take. That is not how it works.
Instead, uh the first, you know, 10, 15,
20 of them
we kind of did them many times
uh in order to get to a point where the,
you know, the standard context that we
present in the in the system prompt and
like the migration goals.txt that I
mentioned in the talk as well as the way
we even break down the tasks and the way
granularity and also the behavior of the
validator and simulator tool itself, um
we had to kind of tune those to get them
to work well enough that the agent was
able to reliably get through. And so we
would encounter situations where the
agent uh
you know,
yeah, thinks that it successfully
migrated and or that it that it
successfully converted, rewrote the code
for a particular metric so that it would
work in the new platform, uh but that
upon, you know, for for like let's say a
set of them, it would say, "Okay,
finished number one. Great. Okay, try
number two. Great, did number two." and
then we'd let it go until it had done uh
several of them and then we would find
like upon inspection of This is
obviously before shipping any of that
code. We would find that like, well,
there are some problems here in what the
agent did and so we would have to go
back and like re
rewrite, add certain things um to the
context and improve the behavior of the
validator and simulator so that from
that point on the, you know, the bot
would be able to do a better job of
producing the code. And another thing I
guess you can find is cases where the
agent would get stuck because it knows
that it's not able to make progress on a
particular task and there could be many
reasons why that would happen and an
example that I like to talk about is
like if the agent just doesn't have
sufficient uh test data for that
particular case, it will struggle to be
able to confirm that the code that it
tried to rewrite is actually going to
work, which is a similar problem that a
human engineer could have if they're
trying to write a new, you know, version
of some code fits the new paradigm, but
where they don't have sufficient test
data to be able to confirm that it's
going to behave in the same way. So
making sure the agent has that context.
Yeah, absolutely. And I guess I guess,
you know, in your in your session, the
session title was migrating legacy code
in weeks instead of years. Did you Do
you have any thoughts in terms of well,
actually how much time Well, first of
all, how long was that process? And I
guess secondly, how long do you think it
would have been had you not have used AI
as as a part of that? So we talked about
the number of metrics I mentioned in the
talk is 247
metrics that were moved into the new
platform. The it really does go very
very quickly once you get that flywheel
running using the approach that we're
talking about. This is part of like once
you, you know, get that assembly line
working where you have sufficient
context in there and the right tools for
context acquisition and the right tools
for validation, you can get
pretty good agents to run your whole
migration really fast. So in terms of
how long it took, I would say that like
the first 20 or 30, like I mentioned
before,
as well as getting those tools and those
fixtures right,
probably took
one to two months. Trying to remember is
my exact
estimates there. The once those things
were in place,
going from that 20 or 30 point all the
way to almost the end of that list
metrics was really fast. So it was like
just a few weeks. And it would be The
reason that you what's so compelling
about this is that as we talked about in
the talk,
anytime you would be needing have an
engineer, you know, read the code in one
language,
look at the underlying data, make sure
that the logic can be captured and put
into a new abstraction, like that that
would be like working after assigning an
engineer that is tasked with stretch out
over a long period of time. The way we
estimated like I said in the talk, it
would take quarters
to do that kind of work where you're
going to have engineers
migrate all that code into a new
platform.
>> And abstract them potentially from a
future product work or anything else
that Right. So I mean, that's time an
engineer could be spending working on
something else, but there's also a sense
of like agility that I want to kind of
people to take away from this where like
a lot of companies and also where I've
worked in the past, like there are often
you know, there are some big migrations
that are deemed high enough priority to
actually
uh to actually kick off and do despite
the huge costs that these things used to
take, but there's also a bunch of other
kinds of tech debt cleanups and like
um
you might almost say desire to migrate
something to use a a better foundation,
but where engineering teams struggle to
prioritize those things because of how
long they take. Yeah. And so Mm. trying
to say here that if you can break down
that problem in the right way, like we
talked about in the talk, you might be
able to do those migrations that you've
been wanting to do Yeah. much faster
than you might have been able to do them
in the past. So it kind of hopefully
helps people think about their strategy
a little differently than we have now.
Amazing. David, thank you so much. Um
and by the way, ServiceTitan they're
hiring right now at the time of
recording. That's right. At the time of
recording, we're hiring.
Uh so yeah, folks find me on LinkedIn.
You can reach out if you're interested.
There's a lot of great stuff that we're
doing here, so. Amazing. David, thank
you so much. Appreciate the amazing
session you gave yesterday. Thank you
for giving us some time, and enjoy the
rest of QCon. Thank you so much.
Appreciate it. Hi there. Joining me this
time is Wes Rice, and Wes is technical
principal at ThoughtWorks. Wes, welcome
to the podcast.
>> Thank you. It was great to be here. I'm
excited to be on it. Tell us a little
bit about what you do at ThoughtWorks.
Yeah, great. So, I'm a technical
principal. We call them technical
partners as well. And so, what I
basically do is I lead an account,
all the technical aspects of an account.
So, on this particular account I'm
leading, it's a large state organization
in the United States. I've got about 10
developers, about 18 people total on the
project with design, project, product,
those type of folks. So, we're basically
building a a knowledge graph for state
agency that's using a deep research
agent to build and populate this
knowledge graph. Then we're building
applications to access that knowledge
graph to be able to answer questions for
the state agency. So, I've been doing
about 3 months for this particular
project, and yeah, that's what we're
doing. Awesome. And we I joined your
session yesterday. Really really
interesting session.
The title for
those obviously not at QCon, AI first
software delivery, balancing innovation
with proven practices. And you talked a
ton about the various different levels
of
using specifications as part of your
software development. Super interesting
both going from I guess using
specifications to assist your
development all the way through to specs
being that kind of that spec centric
piece.
>> Right.
An amazing
amazing blog from Birgitta,
who we had on the podcast before as
well.
>> Absolutely. Absolutely. And you
introduced a really interesting
framework called Ripper or Ripper.
Ripper Ripper Ripper goes back and
forth.
Ripper five.
Why don't you introduce that to to the
audience, and then we can kind of like
delve deeper into It's first be fair, I
didn't come up with it. It was we
discovered it on a blog post or a a
cursor forum that was in I think March
of of this year or so when we first ran
across it. But what it stands for it's
really it stands for research, innovate,
plan, execute, and then review. So, it's
that plan execute model, but it goes a
little bit deeper. And the reason why I
think it's so important is you've been
interacting with an LM, you've been in a
chat console, and you're trying to do
something, and
it has to have the context of what
you're doing. You don't always are in
the same mindset. You may be trying to
research a particular thing, but it
jumps into coding, or you may be
planning and it jump it jumps into
coding, or you're coding and it's it's
not really doing any planning. So, what
the Ripper five model does is it
provides a set of instructions that
you can pass as a command on we're using
cursor. So, we pass it as kind of
property for our our our um
our our IDE to be able to have this
context. So, we give it a command. We
say we're in research mode, and what
that does is it it tells the LLM that
ask me questions, analyze the code base
of where you're at, for example.
But don't do is is important as what it
can do is is what it can't do. Don't do
coding. Don't do planning. Right now, I
just want you to understand what the
code is, what my what my spec is
actually trying to do, so that way I can
provide more details to refine the spec.
So, this Ripper five it's kind of like a
an execution model of how you work with
the LLM, and we do that in pairing with
the with the developer. It's really
interesting cuz like when often when
when you sometimes give an LLM a a task,
it will think it knows enough, it jumps
to the next thing. It's almost like if I
have enough information that I can give
a response,
I'll try and do that rather than
actually thinking, well,
I have enough information to give a
response, but I don't have enough
information to actually give the
response that you as a user want to
provide back. So, in terms of the
context that you give the LLM at that
stage,
I presume it's like similar to rules or
it's it's essentially like a a
step-by-step process to say, look, this
is what you need to do, and then this is
what you shouldn't do. Or if you find
yourself doing this, stop, and
you know,
at least at least complete that before
you say, I'm done, and then pass over to
the next. Is that Is that how it works?
Yeah, so I I kind of jumped straight
into the Ripper five. So, what what we
start with is spec driven development
that as you well know. So, what we
define is a well-defined spec. So, it
has things like acceptance criteria.
We're moving to actually put behavior
driven development type tests in there,
so that way we're getting the test up
front before the code is written. A lot
of times when you have it generate tests
as as you well know, it will fit the
test to the code and not create the test
then the code validates it. So, by
getting kind of BDD style tests up front
and in the specification, it kind of
creates a test driven development type
approach that the spec follows. So, the
first step is getting a well-defined
spec. One of the questions that I often
ask when I talk to people about spec
driven development though is what level
are we talking about? Are we talking
epics? Are we talking stories? Where are
we when we talk about specs? What we're
focused on right now, now remember if go
back, this is a team that we just stood
up with a new account, brought these
people together working with kind of a a
traditional
company, a state organization. So, we
hadn't been here long. We didn't have a
lot of domain knowledge yet about all
the processes that we were doing or how
we were working. So, what we took was
defining a process using Ripper five,
how we're going to work with the LLM
starting with the spec, and then we pair
developers with that process. So, with
that well-defined spec, with that
definition of done, with the acceptance
criteria, with the information that's
there, given that spec, we then go into
that first R stage. And again, this is
just a command that we share with all of
our development team, submodule we pull
into our repo
that means do research. So, do research,
give it the spec, give it the code base
that you're working on.
Make sure you understand what it is that
this is going to do. Ask me questions,
and then we refine that spec. So, as it
asks questions, we put it back into the
spec, so that way we keep refining it.
Then we go to the next stage.
>> Yeah, that's a really interesting point
actually, cuz when you say ask me
questions, I like that, because when we
talk about research, I guess there are
different ways in which the LLM can get
answers. It can kind of like determine
it itself based on its training. It can
do there are a ton of tools that are
available to LLMs these days and agents.
Maybe it does a web search or something
like that. Is it How autonomous is this
research? Is it Is it very interactive
with the user and and kind of like
almost like prescribed by the user, or
can it just go off and and come back?
>> Well, so that's the beauty of it, right?
You do have the tools, so you can use a
tool for web search. If in my particular
case we don't have like an MCP client
that has broader context, but if you did
have context like some of the stuff some
of the products out there that might
provide some context back to it, you
could certainly use those. In the case
that we're doing, it's primarily ask me.
You can do a web search, but generally
it's ask me and then the developer's
providing it back, but there's nothing
that precludes that adding the
additional tools into it so that they
can ask that you can use it. But it's up
in the way that we're doing it right
now, we're using the developer up front
in the process. As we move along, as we
gain more domain knowledge, as we gain
more of the context of how this business
operates, we can start to put evals in
place where we can do things more
autonomously. Right now, we're taking a
very supervised approach being that a
developer, a pair actually, is engaged
with this research.
>> And it keeps that developer in the loop
as well. So, who determines when
research is done? Is that a developer
developer decision to say, yep, we're
good to go?
>> decision. So, we're firmly keeping that
developer in the process. So, once that
research is done, then the next stage of
Ripper is innovate. And that's that part
where you're
you can do things many different ways in
software, right? Like implement this.
What are the ways that you would
implement this? And it might give you
one, two, three, four different options,
and you're like, you know what? I like
two. Or actually, I like two, but let's
make it more invented and make it event
past. You pass that to it. That then
goes back into the spec that refines it,
and that's the innovate. And so, the
innovate stage is still updating the
spec, but it's updating the spec more in
terms of the how Yes. the developer
would want that to be implemented.
>> the spec. It's adding more detail to it.
So, a lot of the tools do some of this
stuff as you go through, but this we're
taking a very simplified this is just
straight markdown. We're interacting
with the LLM and the developer and
enriching the markdown file. And is it
typically I mean, of course, it's just
markdown, so both an LLM or a user can
kind of go in and and play with that. Do
you find people leaning into the LLM
only to make changes, or do you find
people more handcrafting as they go as
well? So, that there's this is a common
question that goes back and forth. What
what I push for is to make sure you go
back to the spec at this stage. You're
firmly in the spec. Now, I do take a
spec first approach. I believe once the
code is developed that the code is the
source of truth. At this stage though,
we're refining the actual spec. Yep.
Yep. Um
So, we've done the innovation. Now it
refines the spec. P. Now, P. P is
planning. So, in planning what we do, if
you think back before AI, if if I had a
story, a well-defined story, and we're
on a scrum team together and say, we're
on this team, we got three or four other
developers. We don't know who's going to
pick up this story. So, we've got this
story, we go into planning, and we look
at this thing. It's like, how are we
going to develop this? And you're like,
oh, it'll be a a react component that we
need to build. There's maybe a service
that needs these methods. We need these
kind of things passed into it. Maybe
this model's there. We might need to
create this repository. We need to do
something to be able to migrate for the
database to do updates, but we like task
it out. We literally break down what's
going to be done. We write the tasks.
So, if you and I aren't here, and
somebody else picks it up, another pair,
they have the same task, they have the
same mental model of what's being
required to do it. We use the same thing
with planning.
So, what we do in planning is once we
have this this stage, there's a command
that will run that's do plan. In what do
plan, we give it the spec. What do plan
will do is it will first break it down
into individual tasks. So, do that same
tasking stage. Then as a pair, we review
those tasks, and we look at it and go,
"Okay, say we're
do these things match what we want, or
do we want to rearrange them, or do
things differently?" Uh one common
example, I think I used in the talk
yesterday, was in the example that I did
when I set up the
when I when it tasked it out, was doing
a Python project, and it didn't set up a
virtual environment first, right? And
then everything I do, I want it set up
in a virtual environment, so I'm
sandboxed off, and nothing's
manipulating my machine. So, the first
thing I did was go back to it and say,
"Hey, add a virtual environment to this
plan."
Going back to the spec, um I'll keep
trying to update that. Sometimes I have
to go to the plan if I can't do the
spec, but what I do is I task these
things out. So, now I have this task,
set up the project, do this this
component that I mentioned, or do this
service that was there, this repository,
the migrations.
I lay all those things out. Once we've
done that,
then what we can do is go to the next
step where we actually create the plan
for that tasks. Um in the in the part
where we actually do the task for that,
we try to keep these things as atomic as
possible, so that way they're they're
very they're like a discrete commit if
at all possible, so they're not leaking
across different tasks. There's a couple
reasons for that. One is they do have
that atomicity, but also we might split
tasks up. You might do one, I might do
another, we might parallelize some of
the work. Some things might be
dependent, we'll build that into a
little task plan that we do through it.
But we'll do that so that way we can
implement each of these things
individually. So, that's that's the
that's the planning stage. Awesome. And
and with with with planning, it it seems
like particularly with things like
Python, for example, there are a number
of common best practices, like, yeah, I
want it I want it to be contained in my
own environment. Um how much of this is
almost reusable across different
projects, cuz there's probably an amount
whether it's styling, whether it's just
ways of working, whether it's you know,
maybe test-driven development, or
whether it's
you know, a stack that the teams are
most familiar with or want to deploy
with. Is there is there like an amount
that you kind of say, "You know what,
for this customer, I want to reuse this
for every single project, therefore I'll
I'll I'll make this some kind of context
that every every project can can reuse?"
For for us in particular, we're using
Cursor, so I'm going to answer it
through a Cursor lens, but how I answer
this really is irrelevant on the
specific tool that you use.
So, what we really start with, even
before you jump into the Ripper 5, is
what are some of the foundational rules
that we're going to establish. So, the
first rules we start with around
documentation,
anything that's created, use Mermaid to
be able to to diagram things. We'll
create create some things like that. Um
there's some general rules that we have
on programming abstractions that we want
to have. Um I know some people will
actually put rules in there about DDD,
for example, if you want to leverage
domain-driven design, or maybe a clean
architecture that you'll add into the
rule set. So, you start there. As you go
through that Ripper 5, and you go into
planning, and you discover those things
that are cross-cutting that you want, we
create rules. Current project I'm
working on, I'm using Spanner. Um so,
there's some rules on how Spanner
operates. So, what I'll do is is I but
I'm still somewhat new to Spanner. So,
as I'm going through that, and I'm
working with Spanner, and I'm doing DML
or DDL, doing updates, and Spanner has a
certain way of dealing with it, I'm
like, "Oh, I ran into an issue here."
So, I add that into my my rule file, I
share that out with the submodule, other
developers pull it in. So, when they're
running another specification that
touches on Spanner, they're picking up
that DML rule that I added into it. So,
we use rules for those particular
things.
>> Gotcha. And how much is that how much of
that is like checked into the
repositories? All of it is. So, what
what we do is just create a submodule.
So, we have
a Cursor
submodule, it's our our rules, we put
rules and commands into that. And then
for all of our repos, we we've probably
got five repos in this one, it's not a
mono repo. And so, what we do is we just
have them clone the submodule, and that
pulls down the latest rules, and then we
apply those rules as we go through them.
Gotcha.
E is execution. Execution. Execution.
So,
I should say
we talked about before that as important
as what you can do is what you cannot do
in each of the stages. So, when you were
in research, innovate, and plan, one of
the rules that you cannot do is execute.
You cannot create code. And that's
important to make sure that the LLM and
the developer are in sync before they
get to that stage of execution and
creating the code. So, now we're in
execution, and now you don't plan
anymore. You follow the plan. That's the
rules that has to actually happen.
>> What if you realize during execution,
actually
Yeah. we need to actually go back to
planning, or we need to go back is it a
process that you can bounce around, or
is it kind of like best done where you
agree completion before you go and
actually makes it a bit messy to bounce
around?
>> It's it's a fine fine line. So, the
answer is it depends. The the general
rule is to go back to the specification
and re-plan. That's the general rule.
But, you know, sometimes LLMs can take a
minute, right? It can think of it. So,
maybe you just want to make a small
change to the plan. It that's frowned
upon, but that's okay. If you do it, you
do it. Once you get to the execution
stage,
it really begins to depend. I am a firm
believer, like, there's different models
that you can take. When you we talk
about spec-first development, um are we
spec-driven development, are we talking
spec as a source of truth where every
change must go to the spec? A lot of
folks A lot of tools out there that that
drive specifications maybe take that
approach. I haven't found that to be
really successful with me, because it
forces you to move up too high in the
abstraction. Um cuz if you're too low,
then you have specifications that start
to collide. So, I haven't found that
perfect balance for me. So, I tend to
use spec-first where spec is used to
define what we want to do in plain
English, we review that, we generate
that when we review what's there.
If there are small changes um that has
to happen. So, one of the techniques
that I picked up with a colleague of
mine when I worked for Equal Expert, uh
Marco Ramilli, and he's the the core
contributor creator of SDKman. He um
what he would do is when the code was
generated,
as you review the code with a pair with
others, and then we drop a to-do in the
code that says, "Hey, I don't want to do
nested for loops here. I want to use
streams to be able to do this." So, drop
a to-do in there, put that definition in
there, and then you would have the LLM
roll through there, pick up all the
to-dos, and update the specification
from that. Interesting technique. Tried
that a few times. That that is a useful
way of doing I've done that. Um other
times,
I will just make the change, because in
in my approach with spec-first and the
approach that we try to follow, the code
is our source of truth, not the spec.
The spec is used to help us get there,
help us align on it, help us to do some
of the thinking, and then just automate
some of the code generation, but the
code is actually the source of truth.
So, as that changes then, do you go back
to update the spec, or the spec is kind
of like a kind of old document at that
point?
>> I Oh, you mean as we go on as we go on?
>> you go forward, yeah. Um so, right now I
we get rid of the spec. We drop the
spec. I haven't completely excluded it
from the code base, but I exclude it
from what we what we ingest, because you
don't want a mixed source of truth
between the spec and then what's the
code. The code is the source of truth.
So, we exclude exclude the spec in what
we analyze. Um but I think it's going to
be completely moved very soon. So, the
execution then just leaves you with pure
code. Does it does it also execute does
it generate any any tests from there at
all, or is that kind of more in the last
stage?
>> So, this is what we were talking about
before with spec-driven development or
with BDD. Like, in many cases, we would
one of our tasks would be to generate
spec. And so, what what you've seen, I'm
sure, is when you generate code, and
then you have a task afterward that
says, "Create 95% code coverage across
this."
What the LLM will do is take the code
and create tests from that, which makes
incredibly brittle code. It makes
incredibly brittle tasks tests. So, what
I then wound up doing as we go through
this is I'm spending so much time trying
to fix these very very brittle tests
that I wind up just get rid of the tests
and re-generate them. That feels
disingenuous. That doesn't feel right.
So, what we're doing right now is we're
pushing tests into the specification.
So, during the planning process, part of
the spec defines BDD. So, when you're
generating code, you're generating the
spec that the tests that go with it. So,
it's together, it's not done as an
afterthought. Which I think at Tesla as
well in our very early learnings, we
originally had kind of like specs with
the capabilities and features
functionality essentially, and tests
separate, and we kind of like realized
well,
and we realized it pretty quick as well,
capabilities is just a different way of
describing a test, and a test actually
describes the capabilities, so we kind
of like merged it all together. Um and
and yeah, I think I think that's
absolutely right. And and yeah, I I I've
seen similar
examples of tests being written for
code, and and those for the absolute
implementation of the code as is, and
and it
it makes it hard, it makes it it puts
LLMs into that into that loop when it
wants to make changes, and things start
breaking, and it it it it it chases its
tail a little bit in terms of what to
what it should change, whereas the test
or the code so forth.
>> Look, what's interesting is the more you
have these conversations like you and I
haven't specifically talked about that,
but we're finding we are all converging
on similar behaviors with specs and and
what goes into the specs and how they're
created. I find that really interesting
that people come from similar
backgrounds and create a similar
approach to this.
>> Yeah, I think it's good. I think it's
good. The R The final R. Final R. R. So,
this is actually something that I think
we miss too much. Um and that's the QA,
right? This is QC. Like we've all
established this pattern of plan and
execute. You're You're seeing them
brought into the IDEs like Cursor now.
All that's there. Ripper expands that a
little bit. And what it does is now
verify the thing that was created
matched the specification. So, in that
review stage, what it does is it looks
at the plan, looks at the code that was
created, and shows you drift. Was there
Did it do what you asked it to do? And
it refers It pushes us back to the
developer and the developer can say,
"Yes,
I actually want that. All right, that
drift is okay. It It does what I want
cuz I'm reviewing and accepting it." In
that case, we have to remediate it, but
what it does is it It verifies that the
plan that was given is what was actually
created and then puts it in the hands of
the developer to decide what to do. And
is that like LLM as a judge style? It
deter It It identifies the the drift
based on what it's seeing versus
actually running some test to to
validate?
>> Yeah, I mean I haven't called it LLM as
a judge, but yes, it is a stage that
says, "Given this plan and the code that
was executed, what does it match?" It
And it has things like created
checklists and so it'll give us our
little green check marks that say it was
all there and red identifies the things
that were that were mismatched. An
interesting trick An interesting feature
of this, though,
is sometimes you want that drift. Like
it actually is something that's
beneficial. I say something in my talk
that the reason why LLMs are so powerful
is because they're non-deterministic. If
it was a pure function, we've had them
for a while.
>> Yeah. If we give it input, it gives us
an exact output, it's called a template.
We don't necessarily need a
non-deterministic behavior from an LLM
to achieve that. So, um sometimes it
will give you something that you're
like, "Oh,
I like that. That's okay."
>> Yeah. So, what In that case, what we'll
do is user review, get that drift, and
then we'll identify that drift and tell
it to go back and update the
specification so that way we can get it
back and we we remediate it that way.
For people who want to
you know, read more about this, uh do
they go to the What What is the best
place? The ThoughtWorks blog or uh uh Uh
to be honest, I we haven't blogged about
it. Um this talk will be published in uh
in a few weeks. It'll be available. Um
there'll be some things I'll put out on
LinkedIn and um yeah, I'll get some
posts out there, but I don't think
there's anything I can point to other
than the Cursor forum where I actually
found it originally, which was March of
But follow Wes on Where's the best
place?
>> I Uh Blue Sky. I'm on LinkedIn
primarily. Um don't don't really use X
or Twitter as much these days, but um
I'm out there. Amazing. Wes, it's been
an absolute pleasure. Thank you, Sam.
You know, I really uh appreciated you
being at the talk and I appreciate the
opportunity to chat with you. Thank you.
[Music]